tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6671019398434141469.post-33126935740955292002012-06-07T16:34:00.000+02:002012-06-07T22:54:32.246+02:00Groovy Goodness: Revisited Getting the Sum of Items in a Collection<p>A while ago I wrote a blog post <a href="http://mrhaki.blogspot.dk/2009/12/groovy-goodness-getting-sum-of-items-in.html">Groovy Goodness: Getting the Sum of Items in a Collection</a>. Today I presented about this little topic as part of the "Groovy Hidden Gems" session at <a href="http://gr8conf.eu">Gr8Conf 2012</a>. One of the attendees noticed the code where we calculate the sum of the <code>Person</code> objects was not working. So it time to revisit this topic.</p><p>The problem with the presented solution is that with more than two elements in the list the code throws an exception. The return method of the <code>plus()</code> method is a <code>BigDecimal</code> so Groovy tries to invoke the <code>plus()</code> method on the <code>BigDecimal</code> class with a <code>Person</code> type argument. And that doesn't exist, hence the exception.</p><p>To fix this we must return a new <code>Product</code> object from the <code>plus()</code> method with the sum of the <code>price</code> property. The code is now:</p><pre class="brush:groovy">class Product {
    String name
    BigDecimal price

    Product plus(Product other) {
        new Product(price: this.price + other.price)
    }
}
def products = [
    new Product(name: 'laptop', price: 999), 
    new Product(name: 'netbook', price: 395),
    new Product(name: 'iPad', price: 200)
]

assert 1594 == products.sum().price
</pre><p>EDIT: I like to thank the people that wrote a comment. The current solution focuses on the implementation of a <code>plus()</code> method in a class to get a sum value. But we can also use a closure for the <code>sum()</code>. In the closure we define the property to calculate the sum for. Or we can use the optional spread operator to get the price property of all products and invoke the <code>sum()</code> method.</p><pre class="brush:groovy">assert products.sum { it.price } == 1594
assert products.price.sum() == 1594
assert products*.price.sum() == 1594
</pre>Hubert Klein Ikkinkhttps://plus.google.com/116304108087638220732noreply@blogger.com2