tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6671019398434141469.post-20556755046374955982014-10-14T06:01:00.000+02:002014-10-14T07:33:56.461+02:00Groovy Goodness: Closure as a Class<p>When we write Groovy code there is a big chance we also write some closures. If we are working with collections for example and use the <code>each</code>, <code>collect</code> or <code>find</code> methods we use closures as arguments for these methods. We can assign closures to variables and use the variable name to reference to closure. But we can also create a subclass of the <code>Closure</code> class to implement a closure. Then we use an instance of the new closure class wherever a closure can be used.</p><p>To write a closure as a class we must subclass <code>Closure</code> and implement a method with the name <code>doCall</code>. The method can accept arbitrary arguments and the return type can be defined by us. So we are not overriding a method <code>doCall</code> from the superclass <code>Closure</code>. But Groovy will look for a method with the name <code>doCall</code> to execute the closure logic and internally use methods from the <code>Closure</code> superclass.</p><p>In the following sample we write a very simple closure as a class to check if an object is a number. Then we use an instance of the class with the <code>findAll</code> method for a collection of objects:</p><pre class="brush:groovy">class IsNumber extends Closure&lt;Boolean&gt; /* return type for closure as generic type */ {

    IsNumber() {
        super(null)
    }

    /**
     * Implementation of closure.
     */
    Boolean doCall(final Object value) {
        // Check if value is a number, if so
        // return true, otherwise false.
        value in Number
    }

}

def list = ['a', 100, 'Groovy', 1, 8, 42.0, true]

def numbers = list.findAll(new IsNumber())

assert numbers == [100, 1, 8, 42.0]
</pre><p>Code written with Groovy 2.3.7.</p>Hubert Klein Ikkinkhttps://plus.google.com/116304108087638220732noreply@blogger.com0